William Remsen Strickland Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
- Music (Box 15-19, OV 1)
  The "Music" series is divided into five sub-series: manuscripts by Strickland (including theory exercises, sketches, and compositions), music annotated by Strickland chiefly for the purpose of conducting, music inscribed to Strickland by composers (including Barber and Cowell), music edited by Strickland for the H.W. Gray Publishing Co., and miscellaneous manuscripts owned by Strickland. Notable among these are a holograph sketch page by Alban Berg, a leaf from an unidentified seventeenth-century manuscript, and a copy of an orchestral transcription of Schoenberg's Variations on a Recitative, op. 40 by Felix Greissle.
  - Manuscripts by WRS (Box 15-16)
    - Air for contralto, Holograph vocal part; [1] p. (Box-folder 15/1)
    - Aubade for viola and harpsichord, Holograph viola part; [1] p. (Box-folder 15/2)
    - Two canticles of praise: Jubilate; Benedictus es domine, Holograph full score; 12 p. (Box-folder 15/3)
    - Two canticles of praise: Jubilate; Benedictus es domine, Photocopied full score of Jubilate; 9 p. (Box-folder 15/3)
    - Two canticles of praise: Jubilate; Benedictus es domine, Printed full scores; 9, 8 p. (Box-folder 15/3)
    - A flower given to my daughter, Holograph vocal part; [1] p. (Call-number ML96.S943)
    - A flower given to my daughter, Photocopied holograph piano-vocal score; [2] p. (Call-number ML96.S943)
    - A flower given to my daughter, Printed piano-vocal score (Call-number ML96.S943)
    - Ione, dead the long year, 3 holograph piano-vocal scores; [3] p. ea.; 1 score transposed to C maj. (Call-number ML96.S943)
    - Ione, dead the long year, Printed piano-vocal score (Call-number ML96.S943)
    - Two medieval carols: Lully lully; Jesus sweet, 2 holograph piano-vocal scores; [5, 6] p. (Box-folder 15/4)
    - Praise to the Lord the Almighty, Holograph vocal score; [1] p.; Arranged by WRS.; Laid in: Sketch for possible verse. (Box-folder 15/5)
    - She weeps over Rahoon, 2 holograph piano-vocal sketches; [4] p. ea. (Call-number ML96.S943)
    - She weeps over Rahoon, Photocopied holograph piano-vocal score; [3] p. (Call-number ML96.S943)
    - She weeps over Rahoon, Printed piano-vocal score (Call-number ML96.S943)
    - St. Anne, 2 holograph short scores; [4, 3] p.; Arranged by WRS. (Box-folder 15/6)
    - St. Anne, Holograph score of brass parts; [3] p.; Arranged by WRS. (Box-folder 15/6)
    - [Sketches, vocal texts, and notes], 130 p. of musical material and 41 p. of vocal texts and notes (Box-folder 15/7)
    - [Student assisgnments and exams] (Box-folder 16/1)
    - [Theory exercises] (Box-folder 16/2)
  - Music annotated by WRS (Box 16-17)
    - Barber, Samuel (Box 16, OV 1)
      - Knoxville: Summer of 1915, Laid in: Separate piano-vocal score inscribed by Barber and autographed by Eileen Farrell. (Box-folder 16/3)
      - Knoxville: Summer of 1915, Inscribed by Barber and autographed by Eileen Farrell. (Box-folder OV 1/1)
    - Blake, William (Box OV 1)
      - Prophecy 1972 (Box-folder OV 1/2)
    - Bowles, Richard W. (Box 16)
      - Prayer and affirmation (Box-folder 16/4)
    - Cowell, Henry (Box 16, OV 1)
      - ...if He please (Box-folder 16/5)
      - Music for orchestra (Box-folder OV 1/3)
      - Symphony no. 16 (Box-folder OV 1/4)
    - Effinger, Cecil (Box 16, OV 1)
      - American men (Box-folder 16/6)
      - Fanfare (Box-folder OV 1/5)
      - Hear my cry, O God (Box-folder 16/7)
      - O praise the lord (Box-folder 16/8)
      - O sing we merrily unto God (Box-folder OV 1/6)
      - Tennessee variations (Box-folder OV 1/7)
    - Handel, George Frideric (Box 16)
      - Messiah (Box-folder 16/9)
    - Howe, Mary (Box 17)
      - Spring pastoral (Box-folder 17/1)
    - Ives, Charles (Box 17)
      - Central Park in the dark (Box-folder 17/2)
      - Robert Browning overture (Box-folder 17/3)
      - The unanswered question (Box-folder 17/4)
    - Keller, Homer (Box 17, OV 1)
      - Chamber symphony (Box-folder OV 1/8)
      - Overture 1792 (Box-folder OV 1/9)
      - The raider (Box-folder 17/5)
      - Serenade for clarinet and strings (Box-folder OV 1/10)
    - Kennan, Kent (Box 17)
      - I saw the white daisies (Box-folder 17/6)
      - I shall not care (Box-folder 17/7)
      - The unknown warrior speaks (Box-folder 17/8)
    - Kochs, Ellis B. (Box 17, OV 1)
      - The automatic pistol (Box-folder 17/9)
      - Life with Uncle (Sam) (Box-folder 17/10)
      - Passacaglia for organ and strings (Box-folder OV 1/11)
    - Sowerby, Leo (Box 17)
      - Psalm CXXX (Box-folder 17/11)
    - Ward, Robert (Box 17)
      - Symphony no. 2 (Box-folder 17/12)
  - Music inscribed to WRS (Box 18)
    - Bacon, Ernst (Box 18)
      - From these states (Box-folder 18/1)
    - Bales, Richard Horner (Box 18)
      - Lines (Box-folder 18/2)
    - Barber, Samuel (Box 18)
      - The coolin (Box-folder 18/3)
      - Two essays for orchestra (Box-folder 18/4)
    - Beach, Amy Marcy Cheney (Box 18)
      - Pax nobiscum (Box-folder 18/5)
    - Cowell, Henry (Box 18)
      - Hymn and fuguing tune: no. 14 (Box-folder 18/6)
      - Supplication (Box-folder 18/7)
    - Howe, Mary (Box 18)
      - Elegy (Box-folder 18/8)
    - Ísólfsson, Páll (Box 18)
      - Chaccone for organ (Box-folder 18/9)
      - Introduktion og passacaglia for orgel (Box-folder 18/10)
    - Kuhnau, Johann (Box 18)
      - Ach Herr, mich armen Sünder (Box-folder 18/11)
    - Sessions, Roger (Box 18)
      - The black maskers (Box-folder 18/12)
    - Sousa, John Philip (Box 18)
      - Circumnavigator's Club waltz (Box-folder 18/13)
    - Sowerby, Leo (Box 18)
      - Suite for organ (Box-folder 18/14)
    - Tournemire, Charles (Box 18)
      - Symphonie-choral d’orgue (Box-folder 18/15)
    - Ward, Robert (Box 18)
      - Lamentation (Box-folder 18/16)
      - Third symphony (Box-folder 18/17)
  - Music edited by WRS for H. W. Gray Co. (Box 19)
    - Jacobi, Frederick (Box 19)
      - Prelude (Box-folder 19/1)
    - Milhaud, Darius (Box 19)
      - Pastorale (Box-folder 19/2)
    - Porter, Quincy (Box 19)
      - Canon and fugue for organ (Box-folder 19/3)
    - Sowerby, Leo (Box 19)
      - Fanfare for organ (Box-folder 19/4)
    - Thomson, Virgil (Box 19)
      - Pastorale on a Christmas plainsong (Box-folder 19/5)
  - Music owned by WRS (Box 19)
    - Anonymous (Box 19)
      - Ave verum corpus, Manuscript fragment; [2] p. (Box-folder 19/6)
    - Barrows, John (Box 19)
      - Chorale fantasy: Jesu meine Freund, Holograph manuscript score; 6 p. (Box-folder 19/7)
    - Berg, Alban (Box 19)
      - Wozzeck, Holograph manuscript sketch; [2] p. (Box-folder 19/8)
    - Boulanger, Lili (Box 19)
      - Psaume 24, Arranger's holograph manuscript score for brass and chorus; 18 p.; Chorus line not present.; On t.p.: Scored by R.C. (Box-folder 19/9)
    - Keller, Homer (Box 19)
      - Five pieces for clarinet and bassoon, Holograph manuscript score; 7 p. (Box-folder 19/10)
      - Five pieces for clarinet and bassoon, Photocopied holograph manuscript score; 6 p. (Box-folder 19/10)
      - Six preludes for piano, Photocopied holograph manuscript score; [8] p. (Box-folder 19/11)
      - Symphony no. 4, Photocopied holograph manuscript short score of 3rd movement; [5] p. (Box-folder 19/12)
      - [Sketches], 2 holograph manuscripts; [1] p. ea. (Box-folder 19/13)
    - Kennan, Kent (Box OV 1)
      - Sonatina for piano, Photocopied holograph manuscript score; 11 p. (Box-folder OV 1/12)
    - Kochs, Ellis B. (Box OV 1)
      - Legend: for oboe and strings, Photocopied holograph manuscript score; 5 p. (Box-folder OV 1/13)
      - Night watch: a dialog for flute, horn, and kettledrums, Photocopied holograph manuscript score; 3 p. (Box-folder 19/14)
    - Kubik, Gail (Box OV 1)
      - Toccata for organ and strings, Photocopied holograph manuscript score; 25 p. (Box-folder OV 1/14)
    - Lewis, Morgan (Box 19)
      - How high the moon, Manuscript score; 6 p.; Arranged for wind band by Sgt. Thomas Merriman. (Box-folder 19/15)
    - Rorem, Ned (Box 19)
      - A sermon on miracles, Photocopied holograph manuscript score; 13 p. (Box-folder 19/16)
    - Schoenberg, Arnold (Box OV 1)
      - Variations on a recitative: op. 40, Photocopied arranger's holograph manuscript full score; 65 p.; Transcribed for orchestra by Felix Greissle. (Box-folder OV 1/15)
- Writings (Box 20)
  The "Writings" series includes articles by Strickland that appeared in Modern Music, The Musical Courier, and other publications. Also present are written-out lectures and speeches, notes for extemporaneous public speaking, notes, outlines, and drafts for Strickland's unfinished book on Charles Ives, and notes on conducting techniques based on his private studies with Nikolai Malko. Strickland’s professional activities and thoughts on a variety of subjects are further captured by two additional series of manuscript materials described separately.
  - Autobiographical materials and resumes (Box-folder 20/1)
  - Published articles (Box-folder 20/2)
  - Miscellaneous speeches and notes (Box-folder 20/3)
  - Notes and correspondence re: proposed book on Charles Ives (Box-folder 20/4-5)
  - Notes re: conducting technique, based on lessons with Nikolai Malko (Box-folder 20/6)
- Journals (Box 21)
  The "Journals" series consists of eleven bound volumes written between 1952 and 1976.
  - 1952-1976, 11 bound volumes (Box 21)
- Datebooks (Box 22-24)
  There are nearly thirty "Datebooks" that provide accounts of Strickland's appointments and itineraries from 1962-1991. These supplement the journals.
  - 1962-1972, 11 bound volumes (Box 22)
  - 1973-1981, 10 bound volumes (Box 23)
  - 1982-1991, 9 bound volumes; 1991 datebook printed as 1982 and altered by WRS. (Box 24)
- Photographs (Box 25-27)
  The "Photographs" series is comprised of several hundred black and white images of Strickland taken throughout his travels in the U.S. and abroad. These, together with the "Posters" series, visually compliment the extensive materials from the regional files. Photographic highlights include several 1963 photos of Strickland and Henry Cowell taken by Cowell’s wife, Sidney, in Iceland.
  - U.S. Army, 1941-1946, 99 black and white photographs (Box-folder 25/1)
  - Wellesley College Conference, 1946 July, 9 black and white photographs (Box-folder 25/2)
  - Nashville, 1946-1951, 67 black and white photographs (Box-folder 25/3-4)
  - Vienna, 1952-1955, 64 black and white photographs (Box-folder 25/5-6)
  - Vienna, 1952-1955, 155 black and white photographs (Box-folder 26/1-3)
  - New York, 1955-1959, 2 black and white photographs (Box-folder 26/4)
  - Japan, 1958-1961, 159 black and white photographs (Box-folder 26/5-6)
  - Korea, 1958, 24 black and white photographs (Box-folder 26/7)
  - Philippines, 180 black and white photographs (Box-folder 27/1-3)
  - Vietnam, 1959, 86 black and white photographs (Box-folder 27/4)
  - American Composers Alliance Award presentation, 1961, 7 black and white photographs (Box-folder 27/5)
  - Iceland, 1963, 11 black and white photographs (Box-folder 27/6)
  - Alice Ditson Award presentation, 1966, 6 black and white photographs (Box-folder 27/7)
- Posters (Box OV 2)
  The "Posters" series contains items from Strickland's travels both home and abroad. Like the photographs they visually compliment the extensive materials from the regional files.
  - Nashville, 1946-1951 (Box-folder OV 2/1)
  - Vienna, 1952-1955 (Box-folder OV 2/2)
  - Japan, 1958-1961 (Box-folder OV 2/3)
  - Philippines, 1958-1959 (Box-folder OV 2/4)
  - Korea, 1958 (Box-folder OV 2/5)
  - Finland, 1964 (Box-folder OV 2/6)
  - Poland, [196-] (Box-folder OV 2/7)
- Scrapbooks (Box 28-36, OV 3)
  A great majority of the bound volumes that form the basis of the "Scrapbooks" series were compiled by Strickland's close friend and supporter, Margaret F. Castle. The Castle scrapbooks include concert programs, newspaper clippings, photographs, and correspondence, most of which have been annotated by Castle herself. A considerable amount of these materials are duplicated in other series, but some original correspondence is found only in these scrapbooks. Other scrapbooks include a publicity book prepared for Strickland in Vienna, a volume of assorted materials from Manila, 1958-1959, and a scrapbook kept by Strickland during his teenage years.
  - Vol. 1, 1942 Aug. 2-1944 Mar. (Box 28)
  - Vol. 2, 1944 Mar. 14-1945 Apr. 4 (Box 28)
  - Vol. 3, 1945 Apr. 5-1946 Feb. 19 (Box 29)
  - Vol. 4, 1946 Feb. 19-1946 Dec. 10 (Box 29)
  - Vol. 5, 1946 Dec. 10-1947 Sept. 25 (Box 30)
  - Vol. 6, 1947 Sept. 25-1948 May (Box 30)
  - Vol. 7, 1948 May-1949 Feb. (Box 31)
  - Vol. 8, 1949 Jan.-1949 Sept. (Box 31)
  - Vol. 9, 1949 Sept.-1950 Feb. 11 (Box 32)
  - Vol. 10, 1950 Feb. 12-1950 Nov. 10 (Box 32)
  - Vol. 11, 1950 Nov. 12-1951 Sept. 21 (Box 33)
  - Vol. 12, 1951 Sept. 21-1954 June (Box 33)
  - Vol. 13, 1954 Mar.-1955 July (Box 34)
  - Oddments [i.e. Odds and ends], vol. 1, 1927-1946 (Box 34)
  - Odds and ends, vol. 2, 1926-1950 (Box 35)
  - First concert of the NSO, 1946 Dec. 10, Reception at the Cheekwood. (Box 35)
  - Clippings related to Grace Cathedral, Jamaica, New York, [2] p. only (Box 36)
  - Photographs and clippings compiled for publicity in Europe, In German or with German translations. (Box 36)
  - Clippings from Manila, Philippines, 1958 Sept. 5-1959 Jan. 18 (Box 36)
  - Clippings and photographs related to American organs and New York performances of Stravinsky’s Rite of Spring and Schoenberg’s Die glückliche Hand, ca. 1930, Compiled by WRS. (Box OV 3)
  - Clippings from Manila, Philippines, 1958 Feb.-Mar. (Box OV 3)
- Miscellaneous (Box OV 3)
  The final series, "Miscellaneous" comprises two items, a framed 1958 portrait of Strickland by Clark Bailey and an inscribed copy of Joseph Szigeti’s autobiography.
  - Portrait of WRS by Clark Bailey, 1958, Pencil drawing. (Box OV 3)
  - Szigeti, Joseph. Strings Attached, Inscribed to WRS. (Box OV 3)